A Guide to the Peyton Randolph Papers, 1804-1813.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Peyton Randolph Papers, 1804-1813
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 91.6
13 items.
Peyton, Randolph, 1778-1826.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1991.
Biographical/Historical Information
Peyton Randolph (1778-1826) was married to Maria Ward Randolph (1784-1826) and was the son of Edmund Randolph. He was governor of Virginia for seven days in 1811-1812.
Scope and Content Information
Letters of Peyton Randolph (1778-1826) to his wife, Maria Ward Randolph (1784-1826), with some letters from Maria Randolph and others. Letters mostly personal in nature mention Peyton Randolph's military and law pursuits and his cure at Warm Springs and White Sulphur Springs. Letters also discuss Maria Randolph's "nervousness" and "depression." Also discussed are PR's father's [Edmund Randolph] customizing of a coach and the social world at the Springs.
Arrangement
Chronologically arranged.
Index Terms
Persons:
Randolph, Peyton, 1778-1826.; Randolph, Maria Ward, 1784- 1826.; Randolph, Edmund, 1753-1813.
Subjects:
Spa pools--Virginia--Warm Springs-- History--19th century.; Spa pools--West Virginia--White Sulphur Springs--History--19th century.; Mental illness--Virginia--History-- 19th century.; Carriages and carts- -Virginia--History--19th century.; Women--Mental health--Virginia--History--19th century.
Genre and Form Terms:
Letters.
Geographical Names:
White Sulphur Springs (W. Va.)--History--19th century.; Warm Springs (Va.)--History--19th century.
Contents List
- Mary Meade to Dr. Meade mentions music concert and social events, 28 May 1804.
- Maria W. Randolph, Richmond, to Peyton Randolph, Hanover Court House. Also includes Peyton Randolph's reply, [23 October 1806]
- Peyton Randolph, Portsmouth, to Maria W. Randolph, Hermitage, Amelia. Mentions patriotic or military gathering in Norfolk, 19 July 1807.
- Peyton Randolph, Smithfield, to Maria W. Randolph, Richmond. Mentions his military duty, his 20 mile walk (six of which he rode) and describes Smithfield, 12 July 1807.
- Peyton Randolph to Maria W. Randolph. Mentions his distress over Maria's nervousness. Says to correct her "morbid sensibility." 3 May 1808.
- Peyton Randolph to Maria W. Randolph. Mentions Maria's depression of the spirits. "Unless you are happy, I must be miserable." "I have determined to devote myself to the single pursuit of your welfare." 1 November 1808.
- Peyton Randolph, Stauton, to Maria W. Randolph. Hates lazy people. Going to Warm Springs. Attempts to downplay the imaginary evils he imagines she imagines, 25 July 1812.
- Peyton Randolph, [White] Sulphar Springs, to Maria W. Randolph. Discusses letter writing and the social scene at the Springs. Mentions that Mrs. Campbell, daughter of Patrick Henry is a 'sable goddess' and "commands the greater number of torpid subjects." 6 August 1812.
- Peyton Randolph, Warm Springs, to Maria W. Randolph. Discusses social life at the Springs. Notes that Maria is an "inimitable model of her sex." 4 September 1813.
- Peyton Randolph to Maria W. Randolph. Mentions a visit to a tavern, some gossip, and notes that his father (Edmund Randolph) is customizing his coach, n.d.
- Peyton Randolph to Maria W. Randolph. Suggest Maria exercise and drink bitters. "...Rouse yourself up and lounge as little as possible." n.d.
- [Maria W. Randolph?] to [Betsy Archer], 27 February n.d.
- Silhouette of woman, n.d.